<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>moench.dev</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on moench.dev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 12:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>mongo snippets: array cheatsheet</title>
      <link>/blog/mongo/mongo-array-cheatsheet-values/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mongo/mongo-array-cheatsheet-values/</guid>
      <description>Cheatsheet - Array Of Values A short cheat sheet for working with arrays in mongodb queries and aggregations. Inspired by: Mongo Doc - Update Array Operator
document structure For all following examples we assume a collection named &amp;ldquo;arrays&amp;rdquo; with at least on document of the following structure:
{ &amp;quot;tags&amp;quot;: [ &amp;quot;tag a&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;tag b&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;tag c&amp;quot; ] }  create Creation is very straight forward so we will skip this part here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>powerbi: handling iso weeks</title>
      <link>/blog/powerbi/powerbi-iso-weeks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/powerbi/powerbi-iso-weeks/</guid>
      <description>There are some twist to keep in mind, when working with ISO calendar weeks. The first week of the year is defi
formulars formular for ISO calendar week
WEEKNUM(data[&amp;quot;timestamp&amp;quot;], 21)  Hint: The parameter 21 is not always documented for PowerBi depending on the source.
formular for ISO year
For grouping we need to know to which year a calendar week belongs. It could be that the last week lays in the new year but for aggregation purpose these week counts to the previous year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>w(u)tf-8 german csv and ms excel</title>
      <link>/blog/notes/utf-8-bom/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/notes/utf-8-bom/</guid>
      <description>why german utf-8 is broken The programming world most of the time does not really care about characters which are special in other languages others than englisch. So in Germany we have our all time favorites ÄÖÜäüöß to take care about everytime we work with text documents.
Normally you will have no trouble with text editors, but an burning example is Microsoft Office. To correctly import an utf-8 encoded csv document (with special chars) you have to provide an BOM.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>arduino: how to use the serial plotter of Arduino IDE</title>
      <link>/blog/arduino/arduino-ide-serial-plotter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/arduino/arduino-ide-serial-plotter/</guid>
      <description>the serial plotter labeling the series If you have to print some debug messages in the beginning, the Serial Plotter will interpret these as Series Labels. To clear unneacessary labels, just restart the serial plotter (not the mc). In order to catch up the labels, you have to print them to Serial everytime you print values. So it is garanted that the series labels are recognized.
As seperators you can use a tabulator, a space or a comma.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about: me</title>
      <link>/blog/about/about-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/about/about-me/</guid>
      <description>My name is Max Mönch, I&amp;rsquo;m an engineer, founder and food and coffee nerd.
 what is this site? This is not a classical blog, I&amp;rsquo;m not writing to adress somebody. This are just toughs and projects I work on. If I did something interessting, it probably lands here to not forget it or to share it with some colleages.
my development world Stuff I work with a lot&amp;hellip;
Languages</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mongo fixing broken timestamps</title>
      <link>/blog/mongo/mongo-fixing-stuff/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mongo/mongo-fixing-stuff/</guid>
      <description>convert bson timestamp to date So I&amp;rsquo;m used to create a timestamp for logging in the db when something is created. What should go wrong with using mongo bson timestamp. Let me say it this way. As long as you leave it alone in the database it will happily coexist with all the other stuff.
But if you want to use it in javascript it gets complicated.
What is a timestamp in bson</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>project: working with socket.io</title>
      <link>/blog/projects/coffeinchat/coffein-chat-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/projects/coffeinchat/coffein-chat-1/</guid>
      <description>CC or CoffeinChat In a project im working on I recently got asked how we could implement a chat by ourselfs. We work a lot with GCP in this Project an so the first tough was to implement it with the help of firebase.
But because of the ongoing debate about GDPR we skipped the easy way and tough about the critical stuff in a chat: The live reload aka pushing news to the client.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>make ftp working with ssh without changing permissions</title>
      <link>/blog/notes/ftp-without-chmod/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/notes/ftp-without-chmod/</guid>
      <description>the problem If you want to disable your root user of the maschine being accessed via SSH you probably ran into Problems with SFTP on your server. As long you use the root user of the maschine your SFTP will work fine, but if you change your user you will get into trouble.
I&amp;rsquo;m working a lot with docker and bind mounts for config files so I can&amp;rsquo;t change the owner/permission of the directory or file I&amp;rsquo;m binding to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mongo snippets: arrays</title>
      <link>/blog/mongo/mongo-snippets-arrays/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 19:23:49 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mongo/mongo-snippets-arrays/</guid>
      <description>extract only subset of embedded documents Sometimes we want to extract not all embedded documents from a matched documents. Imagine a object chatroom:
{ _id: ObjectId(&#39;5f687ba6a93aeddc476ea157&#39;), ... messages: Array&amp;lt;Messages&amp;gt; }  The messages look like this:
{ sender: Reference, send_at: Date payload: &amp;quot;&amp;quot; }  Now when we want to extract all message before, after a date we could query the Chatroom and filter it in the backend logic, or we can use Aggregation Pipeline.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>