<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>notes on moench.dev</title>
    <link>/tags/notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in notes on moench.dev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 12:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>mongo fixing broken timestamps</title>
      <link>/blog/mongo/mongo-fixing-stuff/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mongo/mongo-fixing-stuff/</guid>
      <description>convert bson timestamp to date So I&amp;rsquo;m used to create a timestamp for logging in the db when something is created. What should go wrong with using mongo bson timestamp. Let me say it this way. As long as you leave it alone in the database it will happily coexist with all the other stuff.
But if you want to use it in javascript it gets complicated.
What is a timestamp in bson</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>make ftp working with ssh without changing permissions</title>
      <link>/blog/notes/ftp-without-chmod/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/notes/ftp-without-chmod/</guid>
      <description>the problem If you want to disable your root user of the maschine being accessed via SSH you probably ran into Problems with SFTP on your server. As long you use the root user of the maschine your SFTP will work fine, but if you change your user you will get into trouble.
I&amp;rsquo;m working a lot with docker and bind mounts for config files so I can&amp;rsquo;t change the owner/permission of the directory or file I&amp;rsquo;m binding to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mongo snippets: arrays</title>
      <link>/blog/mongo/mongo-snippets-arrays/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 19:23:49 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mongo/mongo-snippets-arrays/</guid>
      <description>extract only subset of embedded documents Sometimes we want to extract not all embedded documents from a matched documents. Imagine a object chatroom:
{ _id: ObjectId(&#39;5f687ba6a93aeddc476ea157&#39;), ... messages: Array&amp;lt;Messages&amp;gt; }  The messages look like this:
{ sender: Reference, send_at: Date payload: &amp;quot;&amp;quot; }  Now when we want to extract all message before, after a date we could query the Chatroom and filter it in the backend logic, or we can use Aggregation Pipeline.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>